export default Dpe4 = [

    {
        question: "1. D is the power of the lens , then focal length of the lens is",
        options: ["100",
            "10",
            "1/10",
            "1/100 "],
        correct_option: "100"
    },

    {
        question: "2. Assertion : For a erect object having inverted image , linear magnification is negative.\n" +
            "Reason : Linear magnification is the ratio between height of object and height of image.",
        options: ["Assertion is wrong and Reason is correct",
            "Both assertion and reason are correct",
            "Assertion is correct and Reason is wrong",
            "Both assertion and reason are wrong"],
        correct_option: "Both assertion and reason are wrong"
    },
    {
        question: "6. Which lens has positive power ?",
        options: ["Convex & Concave",
            "Concave",
            "Convex",
            "No power"],
        correct_option: "Convex"
    },
    {
        question: "7. Regarding to curved surface refraction , which of the following is true ?",
        options: ["Distances measured along the direction of the incident light ray are taken as positive",
            "All",
            "All distances are measured from the pole",
            "The heights measured vertically above from the points on axis are taken as positive"],
        correct_option: "All"
    },

    {
        question: "8. Do only convex lens converge ?",
        options: ["There is no chance",
            "No",
            "Yes",
            "We can't say"],
        correct_option: "Yes"
    },
    {
        question: "9. The air bubbles in water behaves like----lens.",
        options: ["Convex",
            "Bi-concave",
            "Concave",
            "Bi-convex"],
        correct_option: "Convex"
    },
    {
        question: "10. In spectacles , which lens used ?",
        options: ["Convex lens & Concave lens",
            "No lens used",
            "Concave lens",
            "Convex lens"],
        correct_option: "Concave lens"
    },

    {
        question: "11. A biconvex lens of focal length 'f' is cut into two curved parts in a plane along the principle axis. the focal length of each part is",
        options: ["2f",
            "3f",
            "f",
            "4f"],
        correct_option: "f"
    },
    {
        question: "12. A plano convex lens made of material of refractive index 3/2 has a radius of curvature 10 cm.When it is placed in a transparent medium of refractive index 3 , it will behave as",
        options: ["A concave lens of focal length 20 cm",
            "A convex lens of focal length 20 cm",
            "A concave lens of focal length 10 cm",
            "A convex lens of focal length 10 cm"],
        correct_option: "A concave lens of focal length 20 cm"
    },


    {
        question: "14. Light travelling from a denser medium to rarer medium along a normal to the boundary",
        options: ["Is not refracted",
            "Is reflected towards the normal",
            "Is reflected away from the normal",
            "Goes along the boundary"],
        correct_option: "Is reflected away from the normal"
    },

    {
        question: "16. The focal length of the Plano convex lens is 2R, Where R is the radius of curvature of the surface. Then the refractive index of the material of the lens is",
        options: ["1/2",
            "2",
            "2/3",
            "3/2"],
        correct_option: "3/2"
    },


    {
        question: "19. The power of a concave lens is",
        options: ["-ve",
            "None",
            "+ve and -ve",
            "+ve"],
        correct_option: "-ve"
    },
    {
        question: "20. What is the name given to line joining focal point , pole and centre of curvature ?",
        options: ["Focal point",
            "Principal axis",
            "Focal length",
            "Focal lens"],
        correct_option: "Principal axis"
    },
    {
        question: "21. A real and inverted image of the same size is formed by a convex lens , when the object is placed",
        options: ["At C",
            "Between F and C",
            "Between F and Optical centre",
            "At F"],
        correct_option: "At C"
    },

    {
        question: "22. Total internal reflection can take place only if",
        options: ["Light goes from optically denser medium to optically rarer medium",
            "The refractive indices of the two media are close to each other",
            "Light goes from optically rarer medium to optically denser medium",
            "The refractive indices of the two media widely different"],
        correct_option: "Light goes from optically denser medium to optically rarer medium"
    },

    {
        question: "24. 1/f = 1/v - 1/u  is formula of",
        options: ["Lens maker's",
            "Magnification",
            "Lens",
            "Mirrors"],
        correct_option: "Lens"
    },


]